好的，欢迎回来，这是浓缩物质课程的第八讲
okay welcome back this is now the eighth
lecture of the condensed matter course
量子力学最奇妙的事情之一是粒子是
one of the more wonderful things about
quantum mechanics is that particles are
波，波或粒子，这意味着我们在学习时所学到的东西
waves and waves or particles and that
means that things that we learn when we
研究固体中的振动波通常可以应用于其他类型的波
study vibrational waves in solids can
often be applied to other types of waves
在诸如电子波甚至电磁波之类的固体中，所以今天我们
in solids such as electron waves or even
electromagnetic waves so today we're
将要研究固体中的电子波，这堂课有点
going to be studying electron waves in
solids and this lecture is a little bit
不合适，因为在课程的后期，我们将花费几天
out of place because later on in the
course we're going to spend several days
研究固体中的电子带结构和一些电子波
studying electron band structure
electron waves in solids and some amount
深度，但我在此插入本讲座的原因是为了指出重点
of depth but the reason I'm inserting
this lecture here is to make the point
我们是否真的在研究同一件事，无论我们是否在研究振动
that we're really studying the same
thing whether we're studying vibrational
或我们正在研究电子电子波
waves or we're studying electron
electron waves it's really very very
类似地，我们还将看到我们今天所做的许多计算是
similar we're also going to see that
much of the calculation we do today is
类似于我们研究共价键时的行为
similar to what we did when we study the
covalent bond which was a wave just
在两个原子之间，所以我们今天要看的图片是
between two atoms so the picture we're
going to look at today is a
一维一维紧密绑定链，这将是非常
one-dimensional one-dimensional tight
binding chain and it's going to be very
类似于我们研究的一维振动链
analogous to the one-dimensional
vibrational chains that we looked at in
最后一对讲座也类似于共价键，所以我们要
the last couple lectures also similar to
the covalent bond so we're going to
想象像这样的链中有一束核，胶水给它们一个
imagine having a bunch of nuclei in a
chain like this and the glue give them a
晶格常数相同原子核之间的距离，我们将添加
lattice constant a distance between
identical nuclei and we're going to add
一个电子到这个原子核链，我们将看到当我们发生时会发生什么
one electron to this chain of nuclei and
we're going to see what happens as we
让电子在不同原子核之间来回跳跃
allow the electron to hop back and forth
between the different nuclei so of
当然，我们必须从哈密顿量开始，因为通常的P平方
course we have to start with a
Hamiltonian as the usual P squared over
2m任期加上它将与R的所有不同核V相互作用
2m term plus it will have an interaction
with all of the different nuclei V of R
减去R sub J，其中R sub J是原子核的位置
minus R sub J where R sub J is position
position of nucleus
J，就像我研究共价键时所做的那样，我们将简称
J and as I did when we studied the
covalent bond we're going to abbreviate
为了方便起见，这些术语称为k4动能，
these terms for convenience this term
will be called k4 kinetic energy and
这些项现在称为V sub J，用于与j DH核相互作用
these terms will be called V sub J for
interaction with the j DH nucleus now
类似于我们研究共价键时所做的事情
similar to what we did when we studied
the covalent bond it's useful to think
首先是关于电子，它仅与单个原子核相互作用，而不与任何原子核相互作用。
first about an electron only interacting
with a single nuclei not with any of the
其他原子核，所以我们写Hoop，我们写k加V sub M作为我们的
other nuclei so we'll write H oops
we'll write k plus V sub M as our
哈密​​顿量，这意味着电子具有其动能，并且
Hamiltonian and that means that the
electron has its kinetic energy and it's
仅与移情的leus交互，当它与之互动时，我们将为其赋予原子性
interacting with the empathic leus only
and we'll give it a atomic when it
仅与原子核M相互作用，所以哈密顿量的本征态
interacts with nucleus M only so the
eigen state of the Hamiltonian which has
与amnok leus进行互动时，我们称其为ket m，
an interacting with the amnok leus we'll
call that the ket m and that will put
蒽CLIA上的电子-好像所有其他核都不是
the electron on the anthony CLIA s-- as
if all of the other nuclei were not
那里有一个标签，如果电子坐在这里就像是它
there at all so a label this cat one if
the electron is sitting here as if it
并且不与任何其他原子核相互作用我们也称其为
and not interacting with any of the
other nuclei we'll call this one too
这个一三等等好吧，到目前为止，好吧好吧，就像我们做的那样
this one three and so forth okay happy
so far okay all right now as we did when
我们研究了共价键，我们将做出一个错误的假设
we studied the covalent bond we're going
to make a bad assumption bad assumption
这就是说这些猫和M是正交的，如果
which is that these cats and an M are
orthonormal this is not too bad if the
原子核彼此分开，因为一个电子坐在这里
nuclei are far apart from each other
because a electron sitting over here in
那里的电子坐姿几乎彼此正交
electronic sitting way over there are
pretty much orthogonal to each other
但是当原子核彼此靠近时，它们就不再正交了，
but when nuclei get close together then
they're not orthogonal anymore and the
我们做出这个近似的原因，即使那些不好的近似是为了
reason we make this approximation even
those are bad approximation is for
简单性如果我们做到这一点，很多计算就变得容易得多
simplicity a lot of the calculation just
gets a lot easier if we make this
假设，而做得更好，您不会学到很多东西
assumption and you don't learn a whole
lot more from doing more properly it's
要做起来并不难，这本书上有一个练习
not that much harder to do it properly
there's an exercise on the book that
引导您完成操作，并且您知道可以通过它进行操作，但是您会
walks you through it and you know you
can go through it if you want but you'll
从这个简化的近似中获得大多数有趣的物理学
get most of the interesting physics out
of just this simplified approximation
好吧，一旦我们做出了这个错误的假设，我们就可以写
okay so once we
made this bad assumption we can write
向下试波函数试波函数与我们所做的非常相似
down our trial wavefunction trial
wavefunction very similar to what we did
sie等于n Phi nna的和的共价键
with the covalent bond which will have
the form sie equals sum over n Phi n n a
原子轨道的线性组合，这是我们使用的等效词
linear combination of atomic orbitals
which is a word we used equivalent to
类型绑定线性组合
type binding linear combination of
轨道或lcao的原子轨道
atomic orbitals of orbitals or lcao
我们正在使每个原子轨道上都有一堆电子
we're making we have a bunch of atomic
orbitals electrons sitting on each
核，我们将使它们与系数v线性组合
nucleus and we're gonna make a linear
combination of them with coefficients v
人们不喜欢这种近似的原因之一是因为您可以
sub n the reason people love this type
of approximation is because you can make
通过向右侧添加更多内容，它变得越来越准确
it more and more accurate by just adding
more things to the right hand side with
变量参数Phi在它们的前面，例如，您可以使用
variational parameters Phi in front of
them so for example you can have an
电子以激发态α位于位点n上，所以可能是1s 2s 2p，所以
electron sitting on site n in excited
state alpha so this could be 1s 2s 2p so
等等，我们可以使基础状态越来越大
forth and so on and we can just make our
basis state bigger and bigger basis set
越来越大，并赋予所有这些系数，
bigger and bigger and bigger and give
all of these coefficients and as we make
基础越来越大，我们得到的越来越多
the basis set bigger and bigger and
bigger and bigger we get a more and more
真正的波函数的精确近似，好吧，这有点
accurate approximation of the true
wavefunction ok this is sort of a
变分方法，因此我们可以通过找到最佳方法来解决基态
variational approach so we can solve for
the ground state by finding the best
系数，那么一旦我们有了基态，我们就可以求解第一个
coefficients then once we have the
ground state we can solve for the first
通过找到最佳系数和最低能量来激发状态
excited state by finding the best
coefficients the lowest energy
正交于我们刚发现的第一件事的系数
coefficients subject to being orthogonal
to the first thing we were just found
依此类推，依此类推，所以现在我们要做的就是写下一个
and so forth and so on so now what we
have to do is we have to write down a
这些系数的内部方程越短，方程又越短
shorter inner equation for these
coefficients the shorter equation again
您要在作业中解决的问题将采用H的形式
something that you will solve for in
your homework will be of the form H and
M Phi M等于e Phi n，它看起来像一个短方程
M Phi M equals e Phi n it you know it
looks like a shorter equation
像薛定inger方程那样的庸医，可能是它的缩短方程
quacks like a Schrodinger equation it
probably is a shortened equation it's
不是真正的较短方程，因为真正的较短方程具有一个完整的
not the real shorter equation because
the real shorter equation has a full
坐在这里的哈密顿量反而我们只有一个矩阵和HM，您可以
Hamiltonian sitting here here instead we
just have a matrix and H M and you can
认为这是真正的较短方程在基础上的投影
think of this as being the projection of
the true shorter equation onto the basis
由这些ket组成，并且我们与之合作，这使得
set made up of these ket's and that we
that we working with okay that makes
感觉它看起来像一个较短的方程，它将像一个较短的方程
sense it looks like a shorter equation
it's going to act like a shorter
等式，您也可以推导出它，所以在这里给出较短的等式
equation and you'll derive it also okay
so given our shorter equation over here
我们现在必须计算这些矩阵元素
we have to now calculate these matrix
elements that go into our a shorter
等式，让我们做，采用我们的哈密顿量并将其除法很有用
equation so let's do that it's useful to
take our Hamiltonian and divide it up
分成几部分，因此我们首先将删除与
into pieces so first we'll take we'll
remove the empty interaction with the
与所有其他原子核相互作用产生的空洞，因此这将是J
empty leus from the interaction with all
the other nuclei so this will be J not
等于MV sub J之所以这样做，是因为我们可以在H上写H
equal to M V sub J the reason we do this
is because then we can write H on the
ket M等于K加cat M上的VM加上与所有其他元素的交互
ket M equals K plus VM on the cat M plus
the interaction with all the other
骆驼上的核V sub J好的，现在我们将ket m定义为本征态
nuclei V sub J on camel okay now we
defined the ket m to be the eigenstate
K + VM的数据，所以这里的内容只是ket M上的原子
of K plus VM so this thing here is just
e atomic on ket M oh good
对此感到满意，然后我们可以将内部产品关闭
happy with that so then we can take the
inner product close up the inner product
在这里有ket n，我们得到e原子Delta和M加和，求和于J
with the ket n over here and we get e
atomic Delta and M plus and sum over J
不等于MV sub JM，这是个有趣的名词，所以这个名词
not equal to M V sub J M and this is the
interesting term here so this term here
只是告诉我们，无论电子位于哪个原子核上
just tells us that no matter what site
the electron is sitting on which nucleus
坐在它上面的电子具有能量e原子，这就是所有
the electron sitting sitting on it has
energy e atomic and this is all the
与所有其他原子核的相互作用现在有一个
interaction with
all of the other nuclei now there's a
这个词可能会发生的几件事一种可能性是N
couple of things that could happen with
this term one possibility is that N
等于M，在这种情况下，这就是告诉你有一些
equals M in which case this is what this
is telling you is that there's some
由于与所有原子核相互作用，位于核M上的能量发生了变化
change in its energy sitting on nucleus
M due to its interaction with all of the
其他原子不是M好吧，这将给我们带来这种东西和能量
other atoms not M okay so this would be
will give this thing and energy we'll
称之为V naught等于和某些VGA不II J不等于M，我猜这些
call it V nought equals and some VGA not
II J not equal to M and I guess these
可能是一团糟，这是与所有原子核相互作用的原因
can be a mess like that and this is so
this is interacting with all the nuclei
不包括M，这是对能量的期望，所以它只是在改变
not including M and it's an expectation
of its energy so it's just shifting its
该特定网站上的能量并不是特别有趣
energy on that particular site that's
not particularly interesting the more
有趣的是发生了什么事并且不等于M，所以在这种情况下
interesting thing is what happens is and
not equal to M so in this case you have
这个术语也许是我应该先称呼这个术语，这就是我们
this term is maybe I should call this
term something first this is what we
之前直接打过电话，我想当我们谈到
call direct before and I guess I call it
D cross when we talked about the
末端的共价键不等于M项，这就是我们之前所说的跳跃
covalent bond for the end not equal to M
term this is what we call hopping before
我们之所以将其称为“跳跃”是因为，我们将赋予它价值
and the reason we called it hopping was
because and we'll give it the value
减去t减去T之所以称为跳变，是因为您认为
minus t minus T the reason we call it
hopping is if you think in the
与时间相关的薛定inger方程类型的电子吸收方式
time-dependent schrodinger equation
type of way you can take on electron
坐在站点m上，并最终到达站点n上，因此该对角项在
sitting on site m and have it end up on
site n so this off diagonal term in the
哈密​​顿量允许电子从一个位置移动到另一个位置，因此我们称之为
Hamiltonian allows an electron to move
from one site to another hence we call
它现在跳了一个近似值，实际上是一个相当不错的近似值
it hopping now an approximation which is
actually a fairly good approximation is
n减去m大于1的跳变为0
that n minus m greater than 1 hopping is
跳变等于0或大约为0，其原因是因为
hopping equals 0 or is approximately 0
and the reason for that is because it's
如果想一想，电子很难一步一步跳到很远
very hard for an electron to hop very
far in one step if you think about it
一秒钟，当我们采用这个矩阵时，我们真正计算的是
for a second what we're really
calculating when we take this matrix
当我们明确写出矩阵元素时，它是某种
element is some sort of when we write
out the matrix element explicitly it's
像这样的东西
something like this
正确，这就是矩阵元素看起来像是胸罩，ket和交互作用
right this is what matrix elements look
like a bra a ket and an interaction now
如果phi n如果N和M相距遥远，那么这些波函数会随着
if phi n if N and M are far apart these
wave functions decay very quickly as you
远离原子核，所以在空间上没有点
go away from the nucleus so there will
be no point in space where both this is
很大，如果两个原子核相距很远，那么就很大，这就是为什么
large and this is large if the two
nuclei are very far apart so that's why
我们可以假设这个矩阵元素将为0，除非N
we can we can assume that this this
matrix element is going to be 0 unless N
和M本质上是邻居，好吧，所以我们现在拥有的是
and M are essentially neighbors okay
good so what we have now is we have this
最后，我们可以在J上写n个和，不等于MV sub JM
a in the end we have that we can write n
sum over J not equal to M V sub J M
等于直接项V，如果n等于M，则不等于n，如果N等于M，则称其为负T
equals the direct term V not if n equals
M we'll call it minus T if N equals M
正负1，因此我们只能跳一个站点，否则跳零
plus or minus 1 so we can hop one site
only and zero otherwise
好吧，好人对此感到满意
okay good people happy fairly happy with
that
好是有人点头有人说有人说是谢谢，我发给你另一个
good yes someone nod someone say someone
say yes thank you I send you another
巧克力，但是我昨天给你一个，很好，好，我们可以拿走
chocolate but I gave you one yesterday
so okay good so we can take our
哈密​​顿量并将其重写为H，因为它是一个大矩阵H nm等于它是一个
Hamiltonian and rewrite it as H as a big
matrix H n m equals what is it it's a
原子加上与所有其他原子核（不包括位点本身）的相互作用
atomic plus the interaction with all the
other nuclei not including site itself
如果您坐在一个网站上，与其他网站互动，
if you're sitting on one site
interacting with all the other ones not
包括你自己，还有另一个名词，Delta n M加一个
including yourself plus there's going to
be another term which Delta n M plus one
加Delta n逗号M减1，所以这里有这个附加项
plus Delta n comma M minus one so
there's this additional term here which
允许您向左跳一步或向右跳一步
allows you to hop one step to the left
or one step to the right with an
振幅很好，所以如果我们说我们是一个很大的矩阵
amplitude a T okay good so this is a
great big matrix if we have let's say we
以nn nu开头，则H为N×n矩阵
have n n nu
to begin with then H is an N by n matrix
和Aiden乘n哈密顿矩阵，我们需要找到其特征值
and Aiden n by n Hamiltonian matrix and
we need to find its eigenvalues so how
如果n为a是a，我们这样做看起来像一个复杂的问题吗？
do we do that that looks like a
complicated problem if n is a is a
很好，我们可以解决与我们所做的非常相似的事情
pretty large number well again we can
solve this very similar to what we did
对于振动链，我们使用非点，这是点上的英文单词
for the vibrational chains we use a non
dots which is an English word on dots
而我们使用他的文件的圆点是到IK的圆点上的平面波
and the on dots we use his file is a
plane wave on dots to the I K and a like
现在，对此首先有一些评论，您可能会期待一个e
this now a couple comments about this
first of all you may be expecting an e
从我们对振动链所做的事情到I Omega T的原因是
to the I Omega T from what we did with
the vibrational chain the reason there's
I Omega T的原因在于我们正在解决与时间无关的薛定inger
no e to the I Omega T is because we're
solving the time-independent schrodinger
方程不是时间相关的薛定inger方程
equation not the time-dependent
schrodinger equation if we were to solve
在时间相关的薛定inger方程中，欧米伽T等于e
in the time dependent Schrodinger
equation there being e to the I Omega T
好的，这就是为什么它在这种情况下不存在的原因，
as well okay that's why it's not there
in this case it's just simpler in
量子力学要与时间无关的本征态一起工作
quantum mechanics to work with time
independent eigen States than it is to
使用与时间相关的波动函数，因此这是第一件事
work with time-dependent wave functions
so that's that's the first thing second
事情是，如果您谨慎点，您可能放下
thing is that you probably if you're
careful you put down a square root of
楼下的大写n，因此这是归一化的波动函数
capital n downstairs so that this is a
normalized wave function the
规范化对我们来说并不重要，但严格来说应该
normalization isn't going to matter much
for us but strictly speaking it should
可能在那里，第三点要注意的是，如果
probably be there and the third thing to
note is that this wave is the same if
您在a上将k移至k加2pi是我们上次发现的
you shift k to k plus 2pi over a is
something we discovered last time the
重要的不是动量而是水晶动量
thing that's important is not the
momentum but the crystal momentum if
你把K移了2 pi，我又回到了同一波
you're shifted K by 2 pi over a I get
back exactly the same the same wave ok
因此，让我们将点插入汉密尔顿式的其中一个步骤，我们得到
so let's take our on dots plug it into
that Hamiltonian one step here we get
ε等于负IK的零，e等于负IK n的负T加1 a
epsilon naught e to the minus I K and a
minus T e to the minus I K n plus 1 a
ee等于负IK，负1 a等于ee等于负IK，因此
plus e e to the minus I K and minus 1 a
equals e e to the minus I K and a so
只需将on点插入Schrodinger方程
that's just plug in the on dots into the
Schrodinger equation
使用汉密尔顿式的形式好吧，这就是我没告诉过的
using that form of the Hamiltonian okay
so it's this is the oops I didn't tell
你这是什么我没告诉你什么我不对这件事感到抱歉
you what this I didn't tell you what II
not is sorry about that this thing here
我叫他不是，所以这是现场能量，它使您可以跳到左跳
I called he not so this is the energy on
site this allows you to hop to left hop
在右边，这是另一面的特征能量
to the right and this is the eigenenergy
on the other side people happy okay good
谢谢你，好，那么你就可以计算出一些因素。
thank you good so then you just calc
cancel out a bunch of factors a bunch of
指数因数，您得到e为零减去2t余弦K a，所以让我们
exponential factors and you get e is e
naught minus 2t cosine K a so let's
实际绘制去，所以这里的PI超过这里的负PI超过这里
actually plot that go so here's PI over
a here's minus PI over a here's this is
能量在这个轴上消失了，然后我们会有一个很好的余弦
energy on this axis energy this is e
naught and then we'll have a nice cosine
看起来像这样的表格看起来像这样，如果您想
form that looks kind like this looks
kind of like this and if you wanted to
您可以定期进一步进行下去，但我们真正感兴趣的是
you can continue it out periodically
further but what we're really interested
进入的是区域1区域中从此处到此处的冲泡中的波浪，因为一旦我们
in is the waves within the brew on zone
1 zone from here to here because once we
走到布里渊区之外，我们只是在复制相同的波
go outside of the Brillouin zone we're
just reproducing the same waves over and
再来一次，如果我们想要不同的波浪，我们可以在
over again and if we want different
waves we have we all the ways within the
*区彼此不同，但是一旦我们走出布朗斯自己
bran zone are different from each other
but once we go outside of the Brauns own
我们开始重复我们已经认为可以的事情
we start repeating things that we've
already considered ok just a bit of
Naaman仓库非常有用，也许我把它放在这里
Naaman cloture which is which is fairly
useful maybe I put it over here an
能带能带是指在每个K中一个情况的一个本征态。
energy band energy band means one case
one eigenstate at each each K in the
青铜自己
bronz own
所以在这里我们画了一个能带，你会记得这看起来有点
so here we've drawn an energy band now
you'll remember this looks a little bit
就像我们解决单原子谐波链时得到的一样
like what we got when we when we solve
the monatomic harmonic chain the
每个原子在每个原子中都完全相同的单链振动
vibrations of a single chain of where
every atom is exactly the same in every
春天与我上次讲解的完全相同
spring is exactly the same I last
lecture when we when we solve the
双原子链或交替链，我们发现有两个分支
diatomic chain or the alternating chain
we found that there were two branches of
激发在这个方向上每个K矢量都有两个正常模式
excitations there were two normal modes
at each K vector okay in this direction
如果我们在这张图片中有类似的东西，其中有两个本征态
if we had something similar in this
picture where there were two eigenstates
低能量的和高能量的，我们会说有两种能量
a low-energy one and a high-energy one
we would say that there are two energy
低能带和高能带我们不使用声波
bands a low-energy one and a high-energy
band we do not use the words acoustic
当我们谈论电子的原因是光学和光学时
and optical when we're talking about
electrons for reasons that will become
一会儿就清楚了，但是将这种分散与我们将
clear in a moment but it is useful to
compare this this dispersion to what we
有了振动振动了单原子链单原子我们有了欧米茄
got for vibrations vibrations the
monatomic chain monatomic we had Omega
平方等于我猜这是两个Kappa / M减去两个Kappa / M余弦ka
squared equals I guess it was two Kappa
/ M minus two Kappa / M cosine ka I
相信这等同于您会看到两种色散看起来
believe it was equivalent to that you'll
see that the two dispersions look
极为相似，但有显着差异，显着差异是
awfully similar but there is a notable
difference and the notable difference is
对于较短的方程式，我们在左侧获得e，
that with the shorter equation we got e
on the left-hand side and with the
振动链，我们的欧米茄平方在左侧
vibrational chain we had omega squared
on the left-hand side the origin of this
不同之处在于，如果考虑时间相关性，则较短的方程式
difference is if the shorter equation if
you think about the time-dependent
薛定inger方程具有一阶导数，而牛顿方程F
schrodinger equation it has one time
derivative whereas newton's equations F
等于MA，加速度是两个时间导数，所以这就是为什么
equals MA the acceleration is two time
derivatives so that's why we're getting
左侧有两个频率，而另一侧只有一个能量
two frequencies over on the left-hand
side but one only one energy on the
当我们在思考薛定inger的时候
right-hand side when we're thinking
about Schrodinger and that actually
当我们拥有
makes a rather important distinction
between the two when we had the
在低能量的振动链中，线性模式降为零
vibrational chain at low energy we got
linear modes coming in down to zero
此图片中零波矢量处的频率
frequency at zero wave vector in this
picture here
如果在零波附近扩展，在电子情况下在电子中
in the in the electrons in the case of
electrons if you expand near zero wave
向量不是负2t然后是小波向量K a的低替代值
vector it's not minus 2t and then low
substitute in for small wave vector K a
像这样平方两个，我们看到这里得到2t，我们得到的是恒定的
squared over two like this we see that
we get 2t here what we get is constant
我对加K的平方乘以T不感兴趣
which I'm not interested in plus K a
squared times T its quadratic at low
余弦所带来的能量，这就是为什么我们不使用这个词
energy as you would expect from a cosine
and that's why we do not use the word
这些低能量模式的声学振动特性
acoustic for these low energy modes for
vibrations acoustic modes by definition
声音模式具有线性分散，频率应与
sound modes have linear dispersion that
the frequency should be proportional to
波矢量是声音的定义，所以这里是二次方，所以我们不
wave vector that's the definition of
sound so here is quadratic so we don't
称之为声学，如果有更高的能量，我们也不会称之为光学的
call it acoustic and we don't call it
optical either if there's higher energy
品牌分支，但是这张照片显示的是能量的二次方波动
brands branches but this this picture of
the energy being quadratic in wave
在其他情况下，vector应该对您相当熟悉，例如，如果您
vector should be fairly familiar to you
from other contexts for example if you
有自由电子，有自由电子，有外太空中的电子飞来飞去或
have a free electron free electrons an
electron in outer space flying around or
它的能量是恒定的，加上h bar平方K平方超过2m K
something its energy is some constant
plus h bar squared K squared over 2m K
平方超过2m，在MK中也是平方，您可以选择C
squared over 2m right it's also
quadratic in M K you might choose C to
如果您愿意，则为0；如果您愿意，则可以选择为MC平方
be 0 if you wanted to or you could
choose it to be MC squared if you're
在思考其剩余质量能量的同时，重要的是
thinking about its rest mass energy as
well the important thing is that it's
它是二次方的，并且波矢量与此处的电子相同，因此
it's quadratic in and wave vector the
same as this electron over here so it
也许对我们有用，以自由电子的方式思考一秒钟
might be useful for us to sort of think
in terms of free electrons for a second
所以我们要做的是定义一个有效质量有效质量M星
and so what we do is we define an
effective mass effective mass M star
使得H bar在2 m星上平方等于T的平方乘以
such that H bar squared over 2 m star
equals a squared times T with this
然后定义我们的能带和我们电子中的能带
definition then for our energy band
and for energy band for electrons in our
能带能带我们仍然有一个常数等于一个常数。
energy band energy band we still have
energy equals a constant same constant
再加上h平方，K平方超过2m星，好吧，它看起来像免费的
plus h bar squared K squared over 2m
star okay it looks just like free
电子，它仍然是K的二次方，至少是小K，但现在是
electrons it's still quadratic in K at
least it's small K but now it's an
有效质量M star而不是电子M的实际物理质量
effective mass M star rather than the
real physical mass of the electron M
好吧，现在您知道应该认真考虑一下
okay now this you know should really
think about this for a second the
我们在这个紧密的绑定链中到达这里的有效质量
effective mass that we're getting here
in this tight binding chain that we're
解算与电子的实际质量无关
solving has nothing to do with the
actual mass of the electron it actually
与原子核之间的跳跃有关，质量得到更大的跳跃
has to do with the hopping between
nuclei for greater hopping the mass gets
较小，跳跃越小，质量就越大，我认为因此
smaller for smaller hopping the mass
gets larger I think and so it has it's
完全与电子的实际物理质量无关
totally unrelated to the to the actual
physical mass of the electron you will
查找您知道的样品系统实际物理系统金属或其他地方
find sample you know systems actual
physical systems metals or whatnot where
质量比电子或电子的物理质量小一百倍
the mass is a hundred times less than
the physical mass of the electron or a
比电子的物理质量大一百或一千倍
hundred or a thousand times more than
the physical mass of the electron
尽管在实际材料中具有有效质量的物质并不罕见
although it's not uncommon to have
effective masses in real materials which
在物理电子的实际质量的数量级上
are on the order of the actual mass of
the physical electron the other thing to
请记住，我们在能带中讨论的K不是
keep in mind here is that the K we're
talking about in the energy band is not
动量，但它是晶体动量晶体动量或或h-bar K是
momentum but it's crystal momentum
crystal momentum or or h-bar K is
如果您将H形杆插入其中，则表示动量很大，这意味着您仅知道我们在
crystal momentum if you put the h-bar in
which means only that you know we're
仅定义我们的动量以晶体波矢量为模
only defining our momentum modulo the
crystal wave vector the reciprocal
如果我在I上将所有内容都移两个pi，则晶格波矢量在两个pi上
lattice wave vector two pi over a if I
shifted everything by two pi over a I
回到相同的物理波，所以它与自由略有不同
get back the same physical wave so it's
slightly different from the free
我们熟悉的最后一件事就是电子波
electron waves that were that we're
familiar with the last thing that I want
这里要强调的是本征态
to emphasize here are the eigenstates
eigenstates
我们的波浪我们的飞机波浪只是波浪现在为什么这很有趣
our waves our plane waves are just waves
now why is that interesting it means
我可以拿一个电子，如果我把它放在某种状态下，那有点像
that I could take an electron and if I
put it in some state here it's sort of a
向左移动，向右移动，这是向右移动，向右移动
left a right moving wave it's a right
moving wave in that right moving wave
延伸到整个系统，这对我们的浪潮是至关重要的
extends clear across the system it's an
e to the i k aien our form of the wave
我从面板顶部滚动下来，但这是一个平面波
which I get scrolled off the top of the
board but it's a plane wave that goes
在整个系统中清晰可见，这也许令人惊讶，为什么
clear across the system and that might
be surprising for a second why well
记得当我们研究索末菲理论时，就有这个问题
remember when we when we studied
Sommerfeld theory there was this issue
固体中电子的散射长度似乎过长
that the scattering lengths of electrons
in solids seemed unreasonably long you
所有这些原子核都带有正电荷，它们遍布各处
have all these nuclei with positive
charges and they're all over the place
到每几埃，您就会遇到带正电荷的原子核
to every few angstroms you run into a
nucleus with a positive charge and yet
电子的散射长度可以是一百埃
the electron has a scattering length
that can be a hundred angstroms a
现在有一个千埃或一百万埃长的模型
thousand angstroms or a million
angstroms long now here we have a model
我们有很多原子核周期性地排列在一起
where we have lots of nuclei lined up
periodically one after the other after
另一个接一个，电子从一个跳到另一个
the other after the other and the
electron hops from one to the next to
下一波，使波在整个系统中清晰可见，在
the next next and makes a wave that goes
clear across the system no scattering at
所有您将观察到的这是一个非常好的波形包
all you would observe this as a
perfectly good wave packet going
整个系统中都没有回散一点点，所以这是我们的第一个
entirely across the system without back
scattering one bit so that's our first
令人惊讶的结果，我们将非常频繁地返回到该结果
surprising result and we're going to
come back to that result very frequently
后来，这个术语大家都对此感到满意
later on in the term okay is everyone
fairly happy with that
是的，还有很多我们尚未考虑的其他事情
yes well there's lots of other things
that we haven't accounted for us for
例如我们可以不谈论它可能会扩散到其他电子中
example it can we haven't talked about
it could scatter into other electrons so
实际上，这是我们不会在整个学期讨论的内容
that's actually in fact that's something
we're not going to discuss all term
因为您可以忽略对其他电子的散射的原因是
because the reason you can ignore
scattering against other electrons is
实际上非常微妙，明年您甚至可能不会学到
actually extremely subtle and you
probably won't even learn it next year
直到1980年代或更晚，人们才对它有所了解
it wasn't understood properly until
probably the 1980s or even later and it
在它之下直到1950年代甚至一点都不了解
was under it wasn't understood at all
not even one little bit until 1950s so
这是一个非常棘手的问题，但是您还可以分散其他内容
that's a really tough question but
there's other things you can scatter
有杂质，所以晶体并不完美，里面还有其他垃圾，
there's impurities so crystals aren't
perfect there's other junk in it and
有振动，所以你可以让电子移动，它们可以撞击
there's vibrations so you can have an
electron moving along and they can hit a
振动声子并从声子上散射出去
vibrational a phonon and scatter off of
a phonon as well so at finite
温度，电子声子的散射经常发生
temperature there's
electron phonon scattering is frequently
限制过程好不好的好问题，我再给你巧克力
the limiting process okay good good
question I give you another chocolate
但是您已经可以了，所以我们要做一个以前做过的练习
but you already have one okay so we're
going to do an exercise we did before
计算计数状态时，我们在计算正常模式时是这样做的
counting counting states we did this for
when we counted normal modes in our
振动链，所以我们将拥有n个原子核，这意味着
vibrational chain so will we have n
nuclei nuclei we have so that means the
我们系统的长度是a的n倍，如果系统的长度是a的n倍
length of our system is n times a and if
the length of the system is n times a
我们大声的情况必须是L乘以P的两个PI的形式，其中PP是
the case we are loud must be of the form
two PI over L times P where P P is an
整数P是大家熟悉的整数
integer P is an integer you guys
familiar with that that notation integer
是的，好的P是整数，所以不同k的数量不同k是
yeah okay good P is integer so the
number of different k's different k's is
等于k的范围不同，k的范围是两个pi
equal to the range of k's that are
different which is two pi over a the
从这里到这里拥有的棕熊除以相邻KS之间的间距
Bruins own from here to here divided by
the spacing between adjacent KS which is
L上的两个PI，a上的L，n不足为奇
two PI over L which is L over a which is
n not surprising the number of different
在青铜器中允许的洞穴数量等于
caves were allowed in the bronz own is
equal to the number of unit cells in the
在这种情况下，整个系统很容易以不同的方式理解
entire system in this case it's easy to
understand that in a different way we
从一堆猫开始，其中有n个和n个，
started with a bunch of cats m there
were n of them and n of these and
这些轨道位于原子核上，一个原子核两个原子核三个
orbitals these were sitting on on nuclei
in nucleus one nucleus two nucleus three
依此类推，然后对角化我们的哈密顿量，得到本征态K
and so forth and then we diagonalized
our Hamiltonian and we get eigenstates K
毫不奇怪，他们中的n个和本征态都很大
and they're unsurprisingly there n of
them and eigenstates we had an m and big
通过大n矩阵对角化，我们得到了n个特征值和本征态
and by big n matrix and we diagonalized
it we got n eigenvalues and eigenstates
好吧，所以您输入n个状态就得出n个状态，这是另一种命名法
okay so you put in n states you get out
n states one other piece of nomenclature
这在这里相当有用这是我想的能量规模
which is fairly useful here which is
this energy scale here which I guess for
我们把它滚动到最上面
our
well I scrolled it off the top it's
其实40知道在哪里，所以它是余弦的2倍，余弦2t
actually 40 see where was it yeah so
it's a 2 times the cosine the cosine 2t
余弦乘以该范围，T余弦从正1到负1，所以
times the cosine is the the range and T
cosine goes from plus 1 to minus 1 so
从Emacs的总范围，我们称它为Emacs，在这里，我们称其为e min
the total range from Emacs let's call it
Emacs here let's call this e min here a
min在这里，因此Emacs Emax减去e min被称为带宽宽度，其中
min here so Emacs Emax minus e min is
known as the band width width which in
这种情况是40好，现在我们该怎么办我们带宽是多少取决于它
this case is 40 okay now what do we what
do we what is the bandwidth depend on it
取决于您跳的次数越多，跳的越大
depends on how much hopping you have the
more hopping you have the bigger the
带宽，所以让我们实际画一些图片
band width
so let's actually draw a little picture
这里的带宽实际上取决于T取决于什么
here what is the bandwidth actually
depend on what is what is T depend on
好吧，我们拥有的东西我们可以改变的是
well the thing we had at our disposal
the thing we could change was the
晶格常数a原子核之间的距离为
lattice constant a the distance between
the nuclei as the distance between the
原子核上升，跳变自然下降，越难跳越
nuclei goes up the hopping naturally
goes down it's harder to hop over a
距离越远，T就会上升
longer distance so T goes up goes up
going this way
好人对此感到满意，然后精力就会这样
good people happy with that okay and
then energy is going to be this way and
然后我们可以画一幅这样的图片，我们从一堆
then we can draw a picture that kind of
looks like this we start with a bunch of
所有原子都具有本征态且能量为e的原子
atoms all having eigenstates with energy
e atomic when the atoms are very far
它们都具有相同的能量电子可以坐在这里
apart they all have the same the same
energy the electron can sit here can sit
在这里，它可以坐在任何一个原子上，并且它的能量总是e原子，
here it can sit on any one of the atoms
and its energy is always e atomic and
有n个本征态，我想它现在可以坐在N个原子中的任何一个上
there are n eigenstates and I guess it
can sit on any one of the N atoms now as
我们将原子靠近在一起，而我们的原子核靠近在一起
we bring the atoms closer together as we
nuclei closer together T is going to
增加，我们将获得一支乐队，如果它从e min到Emacs
increase and we're going to get a band
and if it goes from e min to Emacs here
并且在MN和Emacs之间会有这个本征态
and there will be eigenstates within
this range between MN and Emacs so you
在MN和Emacs之间选择任何能量，那里会有一些本征态
pick any energy between MN and Emacs and
there will be some eigenstates there
好吧，所以这里和这里之间的任何能量总会有一些K有一个
okay so any energy between here and here
there will always be some K which has an
在这种能量下本征态实际上应该看起来有点
eigenstate at that at that energy now
this should actually look a little bit
从研究共价键时开始熟悉
familiar from from when we studied the
covalent bond when we studied the
共价键当电子在一个原子上时，我们有两个带能量的原子
covalent bond we had two atoms with
energy when the electron set on one
原子核中的能量不是，当坐在另一个原子核上时是
nucleus this energy was not and when sat
on the other nucleus energy was anat
然后我们将它们放在一起，我们得到了反键轨道反键，
then we brought them together and we got
an antibonding orbital anti bond and we
在这里得到了一个比原来低一高的键合轨道键
got a bonding orbital bond down here one
lower and one higher than the original
能量，这正是我们在这里拥有的
energies and that's exactly what we have
over here we have a whole bunch of
我们以相同的能量将所有轨道合并在一起，我们允许
orbitals all with the same energy we
bring them together we allow the
电子来回跳动，一些能量下降，而一些
electron to hop back and forth and some
of the energies go down and some of the
能量上升，并散布成一个带，这确实有意义
energies go up and it spreads out into
into a band good does that make sense
是的，希望如此，以便传播到乐队中
yes hopefully
so the spreading into a band is coming
从电子来回跳来跳去，所以现在让我们想象一下
from the hopping of the electron back
and forth so right so let's imagine now
我们不仅有一个我们要考虑的电子，而且我们有
that we have not just a single electron
that we want to consider but we have
我们想要考虑许多电子，因为我们不可能有K个状态K
many electrons that we want to consider
since we had n possible K States K
状态，但每个K状态每个K可以有两个旋转，可以有向上旋转或向下旋转
States but each K state each K can have
two spins can have spin up or spin down
这意味着总共有两个n个电子可以适合我，我可以适合乐队，所以很好
that means there's two n total electrons
can fit I can fit in band okay good so
我们填满所有的K State，您可以用任一旋转填满它们
we fill up all the K State's you can
fill them up with either spin
或自旋向下旋转，因此我们可以在该频带中总共容纳两个n个电子
or spin-down so we can have a total of
two n electrons fitting in that band
所以让我们首先考虑一个，我们将把它放在这里
so let's first consider a we're going to
put this maybe here mono valent mono
每个原子核具有一个电子的价原子，因此总共可以得到
valent atom which has one electron per
nucleus so that will give us a total of
总共n个电子，总共n个电子，并且一半填充，一半填充带
n electrons total n electrons total and
that half fills and half filled band
好吧，如果我们总共有n个电子或每个原子有1个电子，我们将充满
okay so if we have n electrons total or
one electron per atom we will fill up
乐队到这里的一半，现在已经充满了旋转和
the band halfway up to here and this is
filled now with both spin-up and
自旋降落的电子好了现在这张照片
spin-down
electrons alright now this picture of a
半满的带半满的带首先它具有一些有趣的特性
half filled band half filled and it has
some interesting properties the first
东西1有费米表面费米表面um那是什么
thing 1 it has a Fermi surface has a
Fermi surface surface um what's that
费米表面费米表面在这里是填充状态相遇的地方
Fermi surface the Fermi surface is this
point here where the filled States meet
空国家，这里是填充国与空国家交汇的地方
状态，所以它们只是两个，因为它是一维的，实际上只是两个
States so they're just two since it's
one dimensional it's actually just two
费米指出您在其中具有最高能量填充状态的两点
Fermi points two points where where you
have the highest energy filled state in
附近的空状态，因为它具有费米表面，所以有可能
the empty state nearby because since it
has a Fermi surface it's possible to
通过从费米正下方获取一些电子来进行低能激发
表面并将其激发到费米表面正上方，这意味着
surface and exciting it to just above
the Fermi surface okay and that means
就像我们在计算中得出的那样，热容量将与T成正比
that the heat capacity is going to be
proportional to T like we calculated in
Sommerfeld理论，因为您可以很好地进行许多低能激发
the Sommerfeld theory because you can
make as many low energy excitations well
您可以进行许多低能量激发，而可能没有问题
you can make lots of low energy
excitations with no problem maybe less
的-是这是一种金属
of the
- is that this is a metal it conducts
用电，这可能很难想象，但让我们考虑一下
electricity so that's maybe a little bit
harder to to imagine but let's think
关于它的一秒钟在这里，我们所拥有的，我们已经在这里，我们有权利
about it for a second here what we have
is we have over here we have right
移动的电子也许我会给它们贴上标签，因为这些家伙在这里有
moving electrons maybe I'll label them
since this one these guys over here have
正KH横条K在右边，所以这些都是右移右移
positive K H Bar K is to the right so
these are right movers right movers over
在图的这一边，在这里，我们还剩下左动子
here on this side of the diagram and
over here we have left movers left
推动者在这一方面如此积极与消极动量，如果我们
movers over on this side so positive
versus negative momentum and if we if we
施加很少的能量消耗的电场，我们可以采取一些
apply an electric field with very little
energy cost we could take some of the
从这里过来的电子并将它们移动到这里，我们可能会过度填充
electrons from over here and moving them
to over here we could over populate the
右边稍微增加一点，并在下面填充一个左边
right hand side by a little bit and
under populate the left hand side by a
只需花费很少的精力即可完成操作，只需移动费米
little bit it cost you only very little
energy to do so just shift the Fermi
只是一点点的表面，然后就有净电流，所以金属可以移动
surface just a little bit and then you
have a net current so metal can shift
费米表面费米表面实际上以一种方式获得电流
Fermi surface Fermi surface and get
current in fact the way the way it
实际发生的是您应该认真考虑一下
actually happens is that you should
really think about it you apply an
电场和每个电子态在一个方向上加速一点点
electric field and each electron state
accelerates a little bit down in one
方向，因此每个电子都会稍微改变其动量，直到这些家伙
direction so each electron changes his
momentum a little bit until these guys
人口过剩，这些人人口不足，那么你就拥有了
get overpopulated and these guys get
underpopulated and then you have the net
当前，这的确是一种金属，并且确实非常频繁地
current so this is indeed a metal and
indeed it's very very frequently the
单价原子是金属的情况下，我的意思通常是简单的图片
case that mono valent atoms are metals
often I mean a simple picture should
总是真实的，但通常是一价单价物质
always be true but often mono valent
mono valent materials
我们的金属现在进一步让我们回到这里看这张照片的情况
our metals now further let's come back
over here to the case to this picture
想象一下，当我们充满乐队之后会发生什么，所以我们将
and imagine what happens when we have
fill the band okay so we're going to
拿这个乐队，我们要填充一半，现在我们在这里填充这些状态，
take this band we're going to half fill
it now we filled these states here and
我们将这些状态留在此处为空，所以这是一个半满的带，现在是
we've left these states up here empty so
this is a half filled band now this is
与共价键非常相似，它的净能量较低
very similar to the covalent bond that
there is it's a lower net energy when
电子可以定位在两个原子核之间，因为它们正在填充
the electrons can be localized between
the two nuclei because they're filling
只要是键合轨道，只要您不必填充反键
only the bonding orbital and as long as
you don't have to fill the anti-bonding
轨道，所以在这里当您开始让电子来回跳动时
orbital so here when you start letting
the electrons hop back and forth they
与他们开始时的能量相比，可以降低他们的能量
can lower their energy compared to this
energy that they started with this
他们开始的原子能，所以
atomic energy they started with so
there's a tractive force between the
原子核试图使它们彼此靠近，从而使跳跃更加频繁
nuclei trying to get them closer
together trying to make the hopping much
更大，这就是形成金属之间的金属键
greater so that is what's forming the
metallic bond between forms metallic
键与原子核之间的金属键非常相似
bond metallic bond between the nuclei
this is very very similar to the
通过让电子离域来使它们共价键
covalent bond by letting the the
electrons delocalized by letting them
通过散布其波函数来降低其动能
reduce their kinetic energy by spreading
out their wave function it forms a
现在将原子核保持在一起的键合力
bonding force that holds the nuclei
together now
您知道在这张非常简单的图片中，我们遇到的问题与
you know in this very simple picture we
have the same problem that we had when
我们研究了共价键，通过这张图您可以期望
we studied the covalent bond that by
this picture you would expect that the
随着细胞核越来越近，细胞核将变得越来越幸福
nuclei would be happier and happier and
happier as they got closer and closer
在一起，一切都会下降到零距离，那不是
together and everything would go down to
sort of zero distance and that's not
正确，因为我们的某些近似值开始分解我们的其中一个
true because some of our approximations
start to break down one of our
开始分解的近似值是我们假设正交
approximations that this starts to break
down is that we assumed orthogonal
简化假设的轨道
orbitals that simplifying assumption
that bad assumption that we started with
另一个要分解的东西另一个分解的东西是我们
another so that's going to break down
another thing that breaks down is we
忘记了或多或少的核相互作用
forgot about the nuclear nuclear
interaction which is more or less
类似于共价键，这种情况或多或少被直接
similar to the covalent bond it case is
more or less canceled by the direct
相互作用，但是当原子核开始变得非常接近时，
interaction but when the nuclei start to
get very close to each other that
取消不再有用，原子核开始收获全部，因此它们不再
cancellation is no good anymore and the
nuclei start to reap all so they're not
将会无限接近，但这大致是导致
going to get infinitely close anymore
but roughly this is what causes the
结合在金属中，这允许电子散布到许多
bonding in metals it's allowing the
electrons to spread out over many over
许多原子并降低其动能，好开心，好，所以我们可以
many atoms and lower their kinetic
energy okay happy okay good so we can
现在考虑一个更普遍的二价原子二价原子的情况
now consider a more general case of
divalent atoms divalent atoms I guess
更一般地说，这只是二价原子的不同情况，例如
not more general this is just a
different case divalent atoms like maybe
氦氦有两个电子在这种情况下，我们有两个电子和两个
helium helium has two electrons in this
case we have two and electrons and two
和本征态我们可以填充，所以我们得到了一个完全填充的地图填充带
and eigenstates we can fill so we get an
entirely filled map filled band well
好吧会发生什么，然后让我们回到这张照片，现在
okay what happens then let's go back to
this picture so now with a divalent
材料，我们完全充满了这个乐队，我们完全像这样充满
material we completely fill this band
and we completely fill like this
一切都充满了，在这种情况下，充满的乐队非常无聊
everything is filled in this case the
filled band has is very boring the
填充带是惰性的填充带可能是惰性的，如果您认为为什么惰性好
filled band is inert filled band may be
inert why is it inert well if you think
大约可以吸收罐，填充带是否有可能吸收任何能量，
about can absorb can is it possible for
the filled band to absorb any energy the
答案是不，不能吸收任何能量，因为所有状态都已充满
answer is no can't absorb any energy
because all the states already filled
你不能将电子从一种状态来回转移到另一种状态
you can't transfer an electron back and
forth from one state to another to in
为了提供能量或带走能量，所有状态都充满了
order to give an energy or take energy
away all the states are filled it's a
独特的状态，没有什么可以移动的，它可以承载电流吗
unique state there's nothing that can be
moved around can it carry current it
无法承载电流，因为您无法更改左动子的数量
can't carry current because you can't
change the number of left movers versus
正确的搬运工他们都被装满了，所以没有热容量没有热容量
right movers they're all filled so it
has no heat capacity no heat capacity
没有电流，没有电流，也没有金属结合
carries no current carries no current
and it also has no metallic bonding
这又与我们在滑雪时的情况非常相似
and this is again very similar to what
we had in the case of the of the ski
当我们考虑两个氦原子之间可能的键合
when we considered possible bonding
between the helium atom between two
氦原子（如果必须填充键合轨道和反键）
helium atoms if you have to fill the
bonding orbital and the anti-bonding
轨道，您不会获得任何能量，因此，如果我们有一个充满的频段，
orbital you don't gain any energy so
here if we have a filled band you had
两个您填充较低的能量状态，但您必须填充较高的能量状态
two you fill the lower energy states but
you had to fill the higher energy states
也是如此，所以跳楼再也不会给你带来任何好处
too so it doesn't gain you anything to
have the the hopping go up anymore okay
那么你的状况怎么样呢，例如在振动变化的情况下
so how are you doing okay good so as in
the case of the vibrational change that
我们本周早些时候研究过的情况还可能是
we we studied earlier this week you can
also have a situation where not every
原子或您正在考虑的每个轨道都不相同，所以现在让我们
atom or not every orbital you're
considering is the same so let's now
考虑一种情况，其中有两个轨道，每个单位两个不同的轨道
consider a case where there are two
orbitals two different orbitals per unit
细胞并且可以杀死它可以以两种不同的方式或几种不同的方式发生
cell and this can kill can can occur in
two different ways or several different
一种可能的方式是在晶胞中有两个不同的原子
ways one possible way is that you have
two different atoms in the unit cell and
他们有不同类型的轨道，其中有氯原子中的钠
they have different types of orbitals in
them sort of a sodium in a chlorine atom
或像这样的情况在单元格中另一种可能的情况是
or something like that in a unit cell
another possible case is you have one
原子，但该原子上有两个不同的轨道，例如S轨道和ap轨道或
atom but two different orbitals on that
atom like an S orbital and ap orbital or
你想考虑的一个和两个轨道
one s orbital and the 2's orbital that
you want to consider so without actually
详细解决此问题可以告诉您什么频谱
solving this problem in in detail can
show you what the what the spectrum
看起来像散布看起来很像
looks like what the dispersion looks
like it's very similar to the case of
振动链，所以这里的K是这里的PI，这里是负的PI是这里的PI
the vibrational chain so here's K here's
PI over a here's minus PI over a here's
e，您会得到一个类似于我们的声学模式的低能带
e and you get a low energy band
analogous to the acoustic mode that we
进入振动链，您会获得类似于
got in the vibrational chain and you get
a high energy band analogous to the
我们在振动链中拥有的光学模式
optical mode that we had in the
vibrational chain okay that's supposed
看起来很对称道歉，所以现在我们有两个
to look symmetric apologize about that
so now we have two
能量带较低的能量带和较高的能量带我们也可以
energy bands the lower energy band and a
higher energy band we could also if we
想要这是缩小区域方案缩小区域方案，我们还可以
want this is the reduced zone scheme
reduced zone scheme and we could also
画在扩展区方案中，我实际上将在这里进行
draw it in the extended zone scheme
which I which I'll do over here actually
扩展区域方案区域方案我们可以画出相同的东西
extended zone scheme zone scheme we
could draw the same thing which would
看起来像这样好吧II，这里的PI等于这里的负PI，这里的两个PI
look kind of like this okay II here's PI
over a here's minus PI over a here's two
在-2上的PI在a上的PI，扩展区域方案的思想是
PI over a here's -2 PI over a and the
idea of the extended zone scheme is to
分散乐队到结核菌素区域，所以这是第一个区域，首先是BZ
spread out the bands into tuberin zones
so this is the first zone first BZ here
第二个在这里，第二个BZ在这里，所以我所做的就是
and the second is out here and out here
second BZ out here okay so all I did was
我拿走了这件作品，并把它移到了这里，移到了两个pi的上方。
I took this piece and moved it over here
by two pi over a and this piece and
由两个PI移到此处，因此每个可能的K只有一个
moved over here by two PI over a such
that each possible K there's only one
一种激励，无论哪种情况，您都应该在
one excitation and in either case your
this is supposed to line up right at the
棕色区域边界此间隙进入此处该间隙进入此处
brown zone boundary this gap comes in
here this gap comes in here at the
青铜自己的边界请注意，区域边界处有一个间隙
bronze own boundary notice that there's
a gap right at the zone boundary and
如果您将它们放在一起并斜视一下，这不是偶然的
it's not coincidental that if you sort
of put this together and squint your
眼睛看起来像一个整体抛物线，那么自由电子可能具有
eyes this looks like one overall
parabola then a free electron might have
但是您已经在区域边界处打开了空白，我们将解释为什么
but you've opened up gaps at the zone
boundary and we'll explain why that is
在学期后期，您可能会想到的一件事是
later on in the term now one thing that
you might consider here is suppose
假设晶胞具有三个电子
suppose the unit cell unit cell has
three electrons
里面有三个电子那么会发生什么然后你填满整个
has three electrons in it well then what
happens then you fill up the entire
带有自旋和自旋电子的低能带，你有一半的
lower band with both spin-up and
spin-down electrons and you have half of
上面的乐队被填满，这里的一半乐队被填满
the upper band filled up to here and
half of the upper band here is filled
填满了上部频段的一半，所以您填满了下部频段，而​​它填充了一半
filled up half of the upper band so you
filled the lower band and it filled half
您会注意到我们已经完全填满了较低频段
of the upper band well you'll notice
that we have entirely fill lower band
较低的频带是惰性的较低的频带是惰性的，我们只需要担心
the lower band is inert lower band is
inert and we only need to worry if we're
考虑运输特性或没有特定热量的热特性
thinking about transport properties or
heat properties that no specific heat
热容量之类的，我们只需要担心上频带
heat capacity something like that we
only have to worry about the upper band
因为较低的频段至少是惰性的，除非您给它一个
because the lower band is completely
inert at least unless you give it an
激发下层频段到上层频段的巨大能量
enormous energy to excite things out of
the lower band and up to the upper band
能量很高，因为这些间隙通常很大，您可以忽略
very high energy because these gaps are
typically very large you can just ignore
整个较低的频段，只担心较高频段的电子
the lower band altogether and only worry
about the electrons in the upper band
但这实际上是这些问题之一的答案之一
but this is actually this is actually
the answer to one of those questions one
我们在本学期早期写下的这些难题中
of these puzzles that we wrote down
earlier in the term and the puzzle from
这个学期的早期是为什么您有时不必担心
earlier in the term was why is it that
you sometimes don't have to worry about
核心电子如果电子在核心轨道中，为什么可以丢
core electrons if electrons are in core
orbitals why is it you can just throw
当你数电子时，它们就消失了。你知道钠只计算一个
them away when you're counting electrons
you know for sodium you only count one
尝试时，每个原子每个单位的电子，而不是每个原子11个电子
electron per unit per per atom and not
11 electrons per atom when you're trying
计算金属密度的原因是因为基本上
to calculate the metallic density and
the reason is because basically those
其他电子完全充满了能带，能带变得惰性，
other electrons are completely filling
bands and the band's become inert and
只是你知道不是像热容这样有趣的物理学的一部分
just you know aren't part of the
interesting physics like heat capacity
然后在这里进行一些其他评论，所以我们得到的是
and and conduction a couple more
comments here so what we've had is that
有这些重要原理是半满的带子是金属
have these sort of important principles
is it half filled band band is a metal
通常是金属，通常是金属，这是一个电子
usually a metal usually metal
and and this is for one electron for
晶胞或实际上每个晶胞有任何奇数个电子，因此它们将是
unit cell or actually any odd number of
electrons per unit cell so they'd be a
每个晶胞电子的奇数个奇数，而偶数个电子
odd odd number of electrons per unit
cell whereas an even number of electrons
每个单位电池的偶数个单位电池的电子数
per unit cell even number of electrons
per unit cell per unit cell you might
认为这是迈克·马累（Mike Male）的权利，可能是绝缘体，因为您会
think that this is Mike male right might
be be an insulator because you would
完全充满乐队，然后你只是一个惰性的情况，但它变成
completely fill bands and then you have
just an inert situation however it turns
在很多情况下，每个电子有偶数个电子
out that there are many many cases where
you have an even number of electrons per
晶胞，但它是金属，可能发生的原因是如果您
unit cell and yet it's a metal and the
reason that that can occur is if you
具有如下所示的波段结构，所以如果您更复杂
have a band structure that looks as
follows so if you're more complicated
像这样的带结构，所以这里是K，这里是PI，这是这里的负号
band structure that looks like this so
here's a K here's PI over a here's minus
PI在上，这是这样的较低频段，然后想象我们有一个
PI over a and here's the lower band like
this and then imagine that we have an
高端频段可以做到这一点，所以您可以分散更复杂的模型
upper band that does this okay so it's
dispersion more complicated models you
可以有一个看起来像这样的色散，特别是上频段滑移
can have a dispersion that looks like
this in particular the upper band slips
低于较低带的下端的顶部，所以如果我每个单元有两个电子
below the top of the lower of the lower
band so if I have two electrons per unit
实际上，您可以充满整个较低的频段，但能量较低
cell in fact you could fill the entire
lower band but it's lower energy to
部分填充该波段并部分填充该波段，那会
partially fill this band and partially
fill this band and that would that would
每个晶胞组成两个电子，而不是完全填充较低的
make up your two electrons per unit cell
instead of entirely filling the lower
乐队，而在这些情况下将这些国家留空
band and leaving these States empty in
that case you have two partially filled
乐队，而不是一个完全填充的乐队，因为你有两个部分
bands instead of one completely filled
bands and since you have two partially
填充的频段，那么您在这里具有低能量激发和低能量
filled bands you then have low energy
excitations here and low energy
激发在这里，所以这个东西实际上变成了金属，所以有
excitations here and so this thing
actually becomes a metal so there are
很多情况下，例如钙，钙甚至是金属
lots of cases of that things like
calcium has calcium is a metal even
尽管它每个晶胞有两个电子，而这正是这种物理学
though it has two electrons per unit
cell and it's exactly this physics
这两个频段实际上正在穿越能量，所以
that's occurring the two bands are
actually crossing an energy so instead
完全填满一个乐队，你有两个部分填满的乐队，好吧，我想
of completely filling one band you have
two partially filled bands okay I think
也许我最好停在那里，我你明天猜猜
maybe I better stop there and I
you I guess tomorrow
[掌声]
[Applause]